<div id="bmbf-dmp" class="d-none">
                        <div id="bmbf-dmp1" class="content-page" id="text_start">
                             <h1 class="text-center"><p class="text-center h1"><center>Datenmanagementplan (Beta test)</center></p> </h1>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Projektname: $_PROJECT</b></span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Forschungsf&ouml;rderer</b>: Bundesministerium f&uuml;r Bildung und Forschung</span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>F&ouml;rderprogramm:</b> </span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>FKZ: $_DMPVERSION</b></span></p>
                            
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Projektkoordinator</b>: $_USERNAME</span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Kontaktperson Datenmanagement</b>: $_DATAOFFICER</span></p>
                            
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Kontakt</b>: $_EMAIL</span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Projektbeschreibung</b>: 
                                

                                <p class="c0"> <span class="c1">
                                    The $_PROJECT has the following aim: $_PROJECTAIM. Therefore, data collection#if!$_VVISUALIZATION and integration #endif!$_VVISUALIZATION#if$_VVISUALIZATION, integration and visualization #endif$_VVISUALIZATION #if$_DATAPLANT using the DataPLANT ARC structure are absolutely necessary #endif$_DATAPLANT #if!$_DATAPLANT through a standardized data management process is absolutely necessary #endif!$_DATAPLANT because the data are used not only to understand principles, but also be informed about the provenance of analyzing data. Stakeholders must also be informed about the provenance of data. It is therefore necessary to ensure that the data are well generated and also well annotated with metadata using open standards, as laid out in the next section.
                           
                          </span></p>
                        
                           <p class="c0">
                               <span class="c1">
                                   The $_PROJECT will collect and/or generate the following types of raw data: $_PHENOTYPIC, $_GENETIC, $_IMAGE, $_RNASEQ, $_GENOMIC, $_METABOLOMIC, $_PROTEoMIC, $_TARGETED, $_MODELS, $_CODE, $_EXCEL, $_CLONED-DNA data which are related to $_STUDYOBJECT. In addition, the raw data will also be processed and modified using analytical pipelines, which may yield different results or include ad hoc data analysis parts. #if$_DATAPLANT These pipelines will be
                                   tracked in the DataPLANT ARC.#endif$_DATAPLANT Therefore, care will be taken to document and archive these resources (including the analytical pipelines) as well#if$_DATAPLANT relying on the expertise
                                   in the DataPLANT consortium#endif$_DATAPLANT.
                           </span>
                           </p>
                            </span></p>
                            <p class="c0 c2"><span class="c1"></span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Erstellungsdatum:</b> </span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>&Auml;nderungsdatum:</b> </span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Zu beachtende Vorgaben:</b> </span></p>

                                <p class="c0"><span class="c1">#if$_EU The $_PROJECT is part of the Open Data Initiative (ODI) of the EU. #endif$_EU To best profit from open data, it is necessary not only to store the data but to make it Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable (FAIR).#if$_PROTECT We support open and FAIR data, however, we also consider the need to protect individual data sets. #endif$_PROTECT
                                </span>
                                </p>
                                <p class="c0"><span class="c1">#if$_DATAPLANT Durch die Implementierung von DataPLANT können Forscher sicherstellen, dass alle relevanten Richtlinien und Anforderungen im Zusammenhang mit dem Datenmanagement eingehalten werden, was zu einer höheren Qualität und Zuverlässigkeit der Forschungsdaten führt.#endif$_DATAPLANT</span>
                                </p>


                            
                            <p class="c0 c2"><span class="c3"><b>Datenerhebung</b></span></p>

                            <p class="c0 c2"><span class="c1"><p class="c0"><span class="c1">Public data will be extracted as described in the previous paragraph. For the $_PROJECT, specific data sets will be generated by the consortium partners.</span></p>
                        
							
                            <p class="c0">
                                <span class="c1"> Data of different types or representing different domains will be generated using unique approaches. For example:</span>
                            </p>
							<ul style="list-style-type:disc;">
                            #if$_RNASEQ
                           <li> <p class="c0">
                                <span class="c1"> RNA sequencing will be generated using short-read or long-read plantforms, either in house or outsourced to academic facilities or commercial services, and the raw data will be processed using estabilished biofirmatics piplines. </span>
                            </p></li>
                            #endif$_RNASEQ 
							#if$_METABOLOMIC
                            <li><p class="c0">
                                <span class="c1"> Metabolomic data will be generated by coupled chromatography and mass spectrometry using targeted or untargeted approaches.</span>
                            </p></li>
                            #endif$_METABOLOMIC #if$_PROTEOMIC
                            <li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Proteomic data will be generated using coupled chromatography and mass spectrometry for the analysis of protein abundance and protein identification, as well as additional techniques for structural analysis, the identification of post-translational modifications and the characterization of protein interactions.</span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_PROTEOMIC 
							
							#if$_IMAGE
                            <li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Image data will be generated by equipment such as cameras, scanners, and microscopes combined with software. Original images which contain metadata such as exif photo information will be archived.</span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_IMAGE 
							
							#if$_GENOMIC
                            <li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Genomic data will be created from sequencing data, which will be processed to identify genes, regulatory elements, transposable elements, and physical markers such as SNPs, microsatellites and structural variants. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_GENOMIC 
							
							#if$_GENETIC
                            <li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Genetic data will be generated targeting crosses and breeding experiments, and will include recombination frequencies and crossover event that position genetic markers and quantitative trait loci that can be associated with physical genomic markers/variants. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_GENETIC 
							
							#if$_TARGETED
                            <li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Targeted assays data (e.g. glucose and fructose concentrations or production/ultilization rates) will be generated using specific equipment and methods that are fully documented in the laboratory notebook. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_TARGETED 
							
							
							#if$_MODELS
							<li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Model data will be generated by using software simulations. The complete workflow, which includes the environment, runtime, parameters, and results, will be documented and archived. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_MODELS
							
							#if$_CODE
							<li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Computer code will be produced by programmers. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_CODE
							
							#if$_EXCEL
							<li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Excel data will be generated by data analysts by using MS Office or open-source software. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_EXCEL
							
							#if$_CLONED-DNA
							<li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> The origin and assembly of cloned DNA will include (a) source of original vector sequence with Add gene reference where available, and source of insert DNA (e.g., amplification by PCR from a given sample, or obtained from existing library), (b) cloning strategy (e.g., restriction endonuclease digests/ligation, PCR, TOPO cloning, Gibson assembly, LR recombination), and (c) verified DNA data sequence of final recombinant vector. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_CLONED-DNA
							
							#if$_PHENOTYPIC
							<li>
								<p class="c0">
									<span class="c1"> Phenotypic data will be generated using phenotyping platforms and corresponding ontologies, including number/size of organs such as leaves, flowers, buds etc., size of whole plant, stem/root architecture (number of lateral branches/roots etc), organ structures/morphologies, quantitative metrics such as color, turgor, health/nutrition indicators, among others. </span>
								</p>
							</li>
                            #endif$_PHENOTYPIC
							</ul>

						#if$_PREVIOUSPROJECTS
                        <p class="c0"><span class="c1"> Data from previous projects such as $_PREVIOUSPROJECTS will be considered. </span></p>
                        #endif$_PREVIOUSPROJECTS
                   
                        <p class="c0"><span class="c1">We expect to generate $_RAWDATA GB of raw data and up to $_DERIVEDDATA GB of processed data.</span></p>
                        <p class="c0"><span class="c3"></span></p>
                        
                        </span></p>


                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Datenspeicherung:</b> </span></p>

                            <p class="c0">
                                <span class="c1">
                                    #if$_DATAPLANT In DataPLANT, data storage relies on the Annotated Research Context (ARC). It is password protected, so before any data can be obtained or samples generated, an authentication needs to
                                    take place. #endif$_DATAPLANT
                                </span>
                            </p>
      

                            <p class="c20">
                                <span class="c1">
                                    Online platforms will be protected by vulnerability scanning, two-factor authorization and daily automatic backups allowing immediate recovery. All partners holding confidential project data to use secure platforms with automatic backups and offsite secure copies.
                                    #if$_DATAPLANT DataHUB and ARCs have been generated in DataPLANT, data security will be imposed. This comprises secure storage, and the use of password and usernames is generally transferred via separate safe media.#endif$_DATAPLANT
                                </span>
                            </p>

                            <p class="c0 "><span class="c1">
                                <p class="c0"><span class="c1">The $_PROJECT will bear the costs of data curation, #if$_DATAPLANT ARC consistency checks, #endif$_DATAPLANT and data maintenance/security before transfer to public repositories. Subsequent costs are then borne by the operators of these repositories.</span></p>
                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">
                                        Additionally, costs for after publication storage are incurred by end-point repositories (e.g. ENA) but not charged against the $_PROJECT or its members but by the operation budget of these repositories.
                                    </span>
                                </p>



                            </span></p>
                           
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Die Dateibenennung erfolgt nach folgendem Standard</b>:</span></p>
                            <p class="c0">
                                <span class="c1">
                                    Data variables will be allocated standard names. For example, genes, proteins and metabolites will be named according to approved nomenclature and conventions. These will also be linked to functional ontologies where possible. Datasets will also be named I a meaningful way to ensure readability by humans. Plant names will include traditional names, binomials, and all strain/cultivar/subspecies/variety identifiers.
                                </span>
                            </p>
                            
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c1"></span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Datendokumentation</b></span></p>
                            <p class="c0">
                                <span class="c1">We will use Investigation, Study, Assay (ISA) specification for metadata creation. #if$_RNASEQ|$_GENOMIC For specific data (e.g., RNASeq or genomic data), we use metadata templates from the end-point repositories. </span><span class="c1">#if$_MINSEQE The Minimum Information About a Next-generation Sequencing Experiment (MinSEQe) will also be used. #endif$_MINSEQE #endif$_RNASEQ|$_GENOMIC</span>
                                <span class="c1">
                                    The following metadata/ minimum informatin standards will be used to collect metadata:
                                    #if$_GENOMIC|$_GENETIC #if$_MIXS MIxS (Minimum Information about any (X) Sequence),#endif$_MIXS  
                                    #if$_MIGSEU MigsEu (Minimum Information about a Genome Sequence: Eucaryote),#endif$_MIGSEU 
                                    #if$_MIGSORG MigsOrg (Minimum Information about a Genome Sequence: Organelle),#endif$_MIGSORG 
                                    #if$_MIMS MIMS (Minimum Information about Metagenome or Environmental),#endif$_MIMS
                                    #if$_MIMARKSSPECIMEN MIMARKSSpecimen (Minimal Information about a Marker Specimen: Specimen),#endif$_MIMARKSSPECIMEN  
                                    #if$_MIMARKSSURVEY MIMARKSSurvey (Minimal Information about a Marker Specimen: Survey),#endif$_MIMARKSSURVEY  
                                    #if$_MISAG MISAG (Minimum Information about a Single Amplified Genome),#endif$_MISAG 
                                     #if$_MIMAG MIMAG (Minimum Information about Metagenome-Assembled Genome),#endif$_MIMAG 
                                     #endif$_GENOMIC|$_GENETIC
                                     #if$_TRANSCRIPTOMIC
                                     #if$_MINSEQE MINSEQE (Minimum Information about a high-throughput SEQuencing Experiment),#endif$_MINSEQE   #endif$_TRANSCRIPTOMIC 
                                     #if$_TRANSCRIPTOMIC #if$_MIAME MIAME (Minimum Information About a Microarray Experiment),#endif$_MIAME #endif$_TRANSCRIPTOMIC
                                     #if$_IMAGE
                                     #if$_REMBI REMBI (Recommended Metadata for Biological Images),#endif$_REMBI
                                     #endif$_IMAGE
                                     #if$_PROTEOMIC  
                                     #if$_MIAPE MIAPE (Minimum Information About a Proteomics Experiment),#endif$_MIAPE  
                                     #if$_MIMIX MIMix (Minimum Information about any (X) Sequence),#endif$_MIMIX  
                                     #endif$_PROTEOMIC 
                                     #if$_METABOLOMIC #if$_METABOLIGHTS Metabolights submission compliant standards will be used for metabolomic data where this is acccepted by the consortium partners.#issuewarning some Metabolomics partners considers Metabolights not an accepted standard.#endissuewarning #endif$_METABOLIGHTS #endif$_METABOLOMIC As a part of plant research community, we use #if$_MIAPPE MIAPPE  for phenotyping data in the broadest sense, but we will also be rely on #endif$_MIAPPE specific SOPs for additional
                                    annotations #if$_DATAPLANT that consider advanced DataPLANT annotation and ontologies. #endif$_DATAPLANT
                                    
                                </span>
                                </p>
                                <p class="c0"><span class="c1">
                            In case some of the metadata is still missing from the documentation from the experimental scientists and data officer. #if$_DATAPLANT Raw data identifier and parsers provided by DataPLANT will be
                            used to get meta data directly from the raw data file. The metadata collected from the raw data file can also be used to validate the metadata previously collected in case there are any mistakes.
                            #endif$_DATAPLANT We foresee using #if$_RNASEQ|$_GENOMIC e.g.#if$_MINSEQE MinSEQe for sequencing data and#endif$_MINSEQE #endif$_RNASEQ|$_GENOMIC Metabolights compatible forms for metabolites as
                            well as MIAPPE for phenotyping like data. The latter will thus allow the integration of data across projects and safeguards that reuse established and tested protocols. Additionally, we will use ontology
                            terms to enrich the data sets relying on free and open ontologies. In addition, additional ontology terms might be created and be canonized during the $_PROJECT.</span></p>

                            
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Legitimit&auml;t</b></span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c1">
                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">
                                        At the moment, we do not anticipate ethical or legal issues with data sharing. In terms of ethics, since this is plant data, there is no need for an ethics committee, however, diligence for plant resource
                                        benefit sharing is considered. #issuewarning you have to check here and enter any due diligence here at the moment we are awaiting if Nagoya (🡺see Nagoya protocol). gets also part of sequence information.
                                        In any case if you use material not from your (partner) country and characterize this physically e.g., metabolites, proteome, biochemically RNASeq etc. this might represent a Nagoya relevant action unless
                                        this is from e.g. US (non partner), Ireland (not signed still contact them) etc but other laws might apply…. #endissuewarning
                                    </span>
                                </p>
                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">
                                        The only personal data that will potentially be stored is the submitter name and affiliation in the metadata for data. In addition, personal data will be collected for dissemination and communication
                                        activities using specific methods and procedures developed by the $_PROJECT partners to adhere to data protection. #issuewarning you need to inform and better get WRITTEN consent that you store emails and
                                        names or even pseudonyms such as twitter handles, we are very sorry about these issues we didn’t invent them #endissuewarning
                                    </span>
                                </p>

                                
                            </span></p>

                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Data Sharing</b></span></p>
                            <p class="c0 c2"><span class="c1">
                                <p class="c20">
                                    <span class="c1">
                                        In case data is only shared within the consortium, if the data is not yet finished or under IP checks, the data is hosted internally, and the username and the password will be required (see also our GDPR rules).
                                        In the case data is made public under final EU or US repositories, completely anonymous access is normally allowed. this is the case for ENA as well and both are in line with GDPR requirements.
                                    </span>
                                </p>
                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">There will be no restrictions once the data is made public.</span>
                                </p>
                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">
                                        The data will initially benefit the $_PROJECT partners, but will also be made available to selected stakeholders closely involved in the project, and then the scientific community working on $_STUDYOBJECT. $_DATAUTILITY In addition, the general public interested in $_STUDYOBJECT can also use the data after publication. The data will be disseminated according to the $_PROJECT's dissemination and communication plan, #if$_DATAPLANT which aligns with DataPLANT platform or other means#endif$_DATAPLANT
                                    </span>
                                </p>
                            </span></p>
                            <p class="c0"><span class="c3"><b>Datenerhalt</b></span></p>
                            <p class="c0 c2"><span class="c1">

                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">We expect to generate raw data in the range of $_RAWDATA GB of data. The size of the derived data will be about $_DERIVEDDATA GB.</span>
                                </p>
    

                                <p class="c0">
                                    #if$_DATAPLANT As the $_PROJECT is closely aligned with DataPLANT, the ARC converter and DataHUB will be used to find the end-point repositories and upload to the repositories automatically. #endif$_DATAPLANT
                                    <span class="c1"> </span>
                                </p>
                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">
                                         Data will be made available via the $_PROJECT platform using a user-friendly front end that allows data visualization. Besides this it will be ensured that data which can be stored in
                                        international discipline related repositories which use specialized technologies:
                                        <p class="c0">
                                            <span class="c1">#if$_PHENOTYPIC For phenotypic data: #if$_edal e!DAL-PGP (Plant Genomics & Phenomics Research Data Repository) #endif$_edal #endif$_PHENOTYPIC </span></p>  
    
    
                                        <p class="c0">
                                            <span class="c1">#if$_GENETIC For genetic data: #if$_GENBANK NCBI-GenBank,#endif$_GENBANK #if$_SRA NCBI-SRA,#endif$_SRA #if$_ENA EBI-ENA,#endif$_ENA #if$_ARRAYEXPRESS EBI-ArrayExpress,#endif$_ARRAYEXPRESS #if$_GEO NCBI-GEO,#endif$_GEO #endif$_GENETIC </span></p>  
                                        
                                        <p class="c0">
                                            <span class="c1">#if$_TRANSCRIPTOMIC For Transcriptomic data: #if$_SRA NCBI-SRA,#endif$_SRA #if$_GEO NCBI-GEO,#endif$_GEO #if$_ARRAYEXPRESS EBI-ArrayExpress,#endif$_ARRAYEXPRESS #endif$_TRANSCRIPTOMIC</span></p> 
                                        
                                        <p class="c0">
                                            <span class="c1">#if$_IMAGE For image data: #if$_BIOIMAGE EBI-BioImage Archive,#endif$_BIOIMAGE #if$_IDR IDR (Image Data Resource),#endif$_IDR  #endif$_IMAGE </span></p> 
                                        
                                        <p class="c0">
                                                <span class="c1">#if$_METABOLOMIC For metabolomic data: #if$_METABOLIGHTS EBI-MetaboLights;#endif$_METABOLIGHTS #if$_METAWORKBENCH Metabolomics Workbench,#endif$_METAWORKBENCH #if$_INTACT Intact (Molecular interactions),#endif$_INTACT #endif$_METABOLOMIC </span></p>
                                        <p class="c0">
                                            <span class="c1">#if$_PROTEOMIC For proteomics data: #if$_PRIDE EBI-PRIDE;#endif$_PRIDE #if$_PDB PDB (Protein Data Bank archive),#endif$_PDB #if$_CHEBI Chebi (Chemical Entities of Biological Interest),#endif$_CHEBI #endif$_PROTEOMIC </span></p>  
    
                                            #if$_OTHEREP and $_OTHEREP  will also be used to store data and the data will be processed there as well.#endif$_OTHEREP  
                                    </span>
                                </p>
                                <p class="c0">
                                    <span class="c1">
                                        The submission is for free, and it is the goal (at least of ENA) to obtain as much data as possible. Therefore, arrangements are neither necessary nor useful. Catch-all repositories are not required.
                                        #if$_DATAPLANT For DataPLANT, this has been agreed upon. #endif$_DATAPLANT #issuewarning if no data management platform such as DataPLANT is used, then you need to find appropriate repository to store or archive your data after publication. #endissuewarning
                                    </span>
                                </p>

                            </span></p>
                        </div>
                        </div>